Rockbridge County Records WLU.Coll.0067
Washington and Lee University, James G. Leyburn Library Special Collections and Archives
- Legal papers, property lists, and misc., 1777-1855 (Box 2, Folder 17-32)
  - Rockbridge County, VA - Slaves Exempt from Draft 1863 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Justice of the Peace Sam Johnston attested that Robert C. McClean appeared before him on January 11, 1863 and certified that his boy William was disabled with swelling and unable to perform public service. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - William Trotter (? Illegible) "man servant named Harrison" severe rheumatism inflammation sworn before Justice of the Peace on January 8, 1863 with doctor's certification (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - J.M. Adams two Negro men incapacitated sworn before Justice of Peace Jan 13, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Statement of Justice of Peace that Joseph A. McClung appeared before him and swore that his "Black Man Charles" had inflammatory rheumatism and was unfit to serve Jan 13, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Doctor's statement from Collierstown Jan 8, 1863 that "Jacob slave of Lafeyette Lehorn (sp?) had a disease of the hands and was therefore unable to serve; flip side includes certification by Justice of Peace on Jan 14, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Statement by Justice of Peace that James Wilson appeared before him on January 12, 1863 and certified that "his boy Sam" had a severe spell of sickness and was unable to serve (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Statement by Justice of Peace that John McKerry appeared before him on January 14, 1863 and certified that "his boy Henry" had a severe case of pneumonia followed by scarlet fever (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Statement by Justice of Peace H. J. Walker that another Walker appeared before him on Jan 7, 1863 attesting that negro man Henry was disabled and unfit for service (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Doctor's certificate Fairfield Rockbridge County "examined Drisley (sp?) the property of Mrs. Tucker of Georgia" very weak from intermittent fever and unable to serve Jan 13, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Doctor's certificate Fairfield Jan 13, 1863 "the boy Alex belonging to William R. Moore has been almost blind for years (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Hugh Barclay statement before Justice of Peace on Jan 14, 1863 that "my boy Hasten has but one leg and not fit for duty" (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Doctor's certificate Jan 13, 1863 "Andy a boy belonging to Alex J. Donald … violent attack of pneumonia" with Justice of Peace notice on reverse (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Doctor's certificate Dec 28, 1862 "I have examined Henry slave owned by Mrs. Hitty Walker… I believe him to be diseased in left lung" (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Doctor's certificate Brownsburg Jan 7, 1863 "Samuel Wilson's boy John is unfit for service – diphtheria (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Joseph Walker, J.P. states that William Walker came before him on Jan 13, 1863 and made an oath that "his negro man Jo is unfit to work" (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Joseph Walker, J.P. states that Betsey Walker came before him on Jan 13, 1863 and made an oath that "her negro man Mark has his feet badly frosted and is not fit to work" ("certificate" also attached) (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - A Patterson, J.P. states that on Jan 9, 1863 Mrs. Ann Cullon came before him and made an oath that her slave Aaron was unfit to serve because of rheumatism and lumbago (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Rockbridge County, VA - Slave lists 1863 (Box 2, Folder 20A)
    - To the Clerk of the County Court of Rockbridge official document dated August 31, 1863 from Executive Department-Richmond-George W. Munford, Secretary of the Commonwealth "A Call for 5,340 Slaves" based on "An Act to amend and re-enact an Act further to provide for the Public Defense, passed October 3, 1862 [passed March 13, 1863] (Box 2, Folder 20A)
    - Owners and number of Male Slaves between 18 & 45 years of age [styled a "List of Male Slaves"] Roll of owners and numbers of slaves as reported by their owners January 14, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 20A)
    - List of owners and numbers of slaves between 18 & 45 as reported by their owners in the western section of Rockbridge (Box 2, Folder 20A)
    - Appraisement of Slaves at Lexington – "We the undersigned Commissioners appointed by the County Court of Rockbridge, to appraise the slaves detailed by said Court for the use of the Confederate States Government, do make the following appraisement of the slaves of this the Lexington District January 24th, 1863:" owners/slaves (by name), ages, valuation [Elisha Paxton… Jack… age 20… $2000.00] (Box 2, Folder 20A)
    - "At Rockbridge County Court January 15, 1863 ordered that the Sheriff of this County deliver the drafted slaves either [sic] to the Commissioners appointed to value such slaves at Lexington on Tuesday next, at Oak Bank on Wednesday next, or at Brownsburg on Thursday next" names of owners with number of slaves [a number of Paxtons, including Elisha] (Box 2, Folder 20A)
    - Receipt for slaves -- Received from the charge of John F. Greenler, Deputy "The following listed slaves who have been assigned by the County to work on the fortifications at Richmond this 21st day of January 1863 to deliver in Richmond (Edward M. Houston, Agent) – names of slaves, ages, owners, and valuations (Box 2, Folder 20A)
    - Valuation of individual slaves Jan 22, 1863 by James Campbell and other subscribers (Box 2, Folder 20A)
    - Receipt for slaves – names of slaves, ages, owners, and valuations – (J.W. Christian, Agent) Jan 21, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 20A)
    - "Appraisement of Slaves at Brownsburg" – "Valuation of Slaves sent to Richmond to work on the fortifications from the lower end of the County of Rockbridge made this 22nd day of January 1863 -by. Patterson, S. Brown, & Henry Jones – names of owners, names of slaves, ages of slaves, values (Box 2, Folder 20A)
    - Receipt for slaves -- Recvd of the Sheriff of Rockbridge County 'The following slaves drafted to work on the fortifications for the defense of the Confederate States which I am to deliver to the authorities at Richmond – names of owners, slaves, ages of slaves, values Jan. 22, 1863 (J.W. Christian, Agent) (Box 2, Folder 20A)
    - List of slaves between 18 & 45 years of age (by owners & number only) in the district of J. Johnston, Deputy Sheriff January 1863 (Box 2, Folder 20A)
    - Appraisal of slaves from Natural Bridge district to work on fortifications January 21, 1863 (owners, "names of Negroes, ages, amounts" January 21, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 20A)
    - Two sheets, one labelled "Slaves Drafted" with misc. names crossed out, the other labelled "Slaves enrolled for draft" but blank. (Box 2, Folder 20A)
  - Rockbridge County - Blank Amnesty Petition Formularies (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Two hand-written "Amnesty Petition" formularies for use in Rockbridge County addressed in blank to "His Excellency Andrew Jackson, President of the United States" July 1865 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Rockbridge County, VA - Surveying Records 1867 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Booklet of hand-written surveying records for Rockbridge County wrapped in a deteriorating copy of The Gazette-Banner newspaper- Lexington, Virginia, Wednesday, May 22, 1867 No. 11. The pages appear to contain a list of plats (119 in all), individuals responsible for the plats, and persons residing on the plats. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Rockbridge County, VA Real Estate Lists 1873 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - "List of real estate within the County of Rockbridge sold on December 1, 1873 for the non-payment of taxes for the years 1865, 1866, 1867, 1868, 1869, 1870, and 1871" including the names of the individual purchasers (Name of Person charged with taxes; quantity of land charged; local description of land; amount of taxes due; quantity of land sold; name of purchaser, amount of purchase money; remarks) signed by J.D. Anderson, Treasurer of Rockbridge County. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - "List of real estate within the County of Rockbridge sold on December 1, 1873 for the non-payment of taxes for the years 1865, 1866, 1867, 1868, 1869, 1870, and 1871" with the Commonwealth of Virginia list as the Purchaser (Name of Person charged with taxes; quantity of land charged; local description of land; amount of taxes due; quantity of land sold; amount of purchase money; remarks) signed by J.D. Anderson, Treasurer of Rockbridge County. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Scrap of paper appears to be a receipt dated March 12, 1873 for a Mrs. Davison involving ¼ bushel of apples (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Tax note – Sheriff of Rockbridge County re: General TJ Jackson (property apparently not in Lexington) with endorsement on back "rec.d March 18, 1871 of Dr. Bartow $16.58 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Rockbridge County, VA - Taxation Records - 1874 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Property statistics Rockbridge 1874 (some comparison data to 1873) (musical instruments, hogs, sheep, horses, etc.) (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Taxation synopsis 1874 (Rockbridge County) statistics (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Printed formulary – "Persons, Property, and other Subjects" for 1873 / for 1874 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Rockbridge County, VA - Unidentified Deed Book (incomplete) 1876-77 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Unidentified Deed Book (incomplete) 1876-77 property granted by E.F. Paxton July 1, 1876 mentioned on Page 8 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Rockbridge County, VA - Misc. 1891-1898 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Democratic Election Ticket – Rockbridge County Virginia Election Day May 28, 1891 County Officers District Officers (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - State Personal Property Interrogatories – 1898 (signed in pencil by John H. Stoner, agt. 1898) (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - State Personal Property Interrogatories – 1898 (signed in pencil by A. Lavell Sept. 23, 1898) (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - State Personal Property Interrogatories – 1898 (signed in pencil by R.A.Howell [Glasgow] Sept. 15, 1898) (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - State Personal Property Interrogatories – 1898 (signed in pencil by N.B.Rees May 28, 1898) (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - State Personal Property Interrogatories – 1898 (signed in pencil by G.D. Edmunds Sept. 15, 1898) (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - State Personal Property Interrogatories – 1898 (signed in pencil by Thomas Bryant Sept. 15, 1898) (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - State Personal Property Interrogatories – 1898 (signed in pencil by W.H. Chiles May 5, 1898) (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - State Personal Property Interrogatories – 1898 (signed in pencil by Mrs. B. Ackerly June 29, 1898) (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Rockbridge County, VA - Tax on Real Property - 1895-1897 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing Tax imposed for County purposes on Norfolk Western Railway Company Natural Bridge District for year 1897 (signed by Charles H. Paxton, Commissioner of Revenue, Natural Bridge District) Sept. 6, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing Tax imposed for County purposes on Norfolk Western Railway Company South River District for year 1897 (signed by Lakey, Commissioner of Revenue, South River District) Sept. 1, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing Tax imposed for County purposes on Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company Walkers Creek District for year 1897 (signed by B. Watson, Deputy for L.L. Watson Commissioner of Revenue, Walkers Creek District) (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing Tax imposed for County purposes on Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company Natural Bridge District for year 1897 (signed by Charles H. Paxton, Commissioner of Revenue, Natural Bridge District) Sept. 6, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing Tax imposed for County purposes on Chesapeake and Ohio Railway and Telegraph Company in the Lexington District for year 1897 (signed by A.W. Varner, Commissioner of Revenue) Aug. 16, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing Tax imposed for County purposes on Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company in South River District for year 1897 (signed by Lakey, Commissioner of Revenue, South River District) Sept. 1, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing Tax imposed for County purposes on the Virginia Iron and Railway Company in the Walkers Creek District for year 1897 (signed by B. Watson, Deputy for L.L. Watson Commissioner of Revenue, Walkers Creek District) Aug. 5, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing Tax imposed for County purposes on the Virginia Iron and Railway Company in Kerrs Creek District for year 1897 (signed by S.H. Moore Commissioner of Revenue, Kerrs Creek District) Aug. 13, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing Tax imposed for County purposes on the Rockbridge Alum and Goshen Railway Company in Kerrs Creek District for year 1897 (signed by S.H. Moore Commissioner of Revenue, Kerrs Creek District) Aug. 13, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing Tax imposed for County purposes on the New York and Southern Telegraph Company in the Lexington District for year 1897 (signed by A.W. Varner, Commissioner of Revenue) Aug. 16, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing Tax imposed for County purposes on Western Union Telegraph Company in the Lexington District for year 1897 (signed by A.W. Varner, Commissioner of Revenue) Aug. 16, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing Tax imposed for County purposes on the New York & Southern Telegraph Company in the Lexington District for year 1895 (signed by A.W. Varner, Commissioner of Revenue) Aug. 31, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing Tax imposed for County purposes on the New York & Southern Telegraph Company in the Lexington District for year 1896 (signed by A.W. Varner, Commissioner of Revenue) Aug. 4, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing Tax imposed for County purposes on Western Union Telegraph Company in the Lexington District for year 1896 (signed by A.W. Varner, Commissioner of Revenue) Aug. 4, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing Tax imposed for County purposes on the Virginia Iron and Railway Company in the Walkers Creek District for year 1896 (signed by L.L. Watson, Commissioner of Revenue for Walkers Creek) Aug. 27, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing Tax imposed for County purposes in South River District on the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company (signed by Lackey, Commissioner of Revenue Aug. 31, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing tax imposed for County purposes on the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company in Walkers Creek District for year 1896 (signed by L.L. Watson, Commissioner of Revenue for Walkers Creek) Aug 27, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing tax imposed for County purposes on the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company in the Natural Bridge District for year 1896 (signed by Charles H. Paxton, Commissioner of Revenue for Natural Bridge District) Aug 31, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing tax imposed for County purposes on Lexington Branch of Chesapeake & Ohio Railway & Telegraph Co. in the Lexington District for year 1896 (signed by A. W. Varner, Commissioner of Revenue) Aug. 4, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing tax imposed for County purposes on Norfolk and Western Railroad Company in South River District for year 1896 (signed by Lackey, Commissioner of Revenue) Aug 31, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing tax imposed for County purposes on the Norfolk and Western Railway Company in the Natural Bridge District for year 1896 (signed by Charles H. Paxton, Commissioner of Revenue for Natural Bridge District) Aug 31, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing tax imposed for County purposes on the Western Union Telegraph Company [Lexington] for year 1895 (signed by A. W. Varner, Commissioner of Revenue) Aug. 31, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing tax imposed for County purposes on the Virginia Iron & Railway Company in Kerrs Creek District for 1895 (signed by S.H. Moore, Commissioner of Revenue) Sept. 2, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing tax imposed for County purposes on the Rockbridge Alum and Goshen Railroad in the Kerrs Creek District for year 1896 (signed by S.H. Moore, Commissioner of Revenue), Sept. 2, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing tax imposed for County purposes on the Virginia Iron and Railway Company in Walkers Creek District for year 1895 (signed by L.L. Watson, Commissioner of Revenue), Sept. 2, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing tax imposed for County purposes on Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad in South River District for year 1895 (signed by Lackey, Commissioner of Revenue), Sept. 2, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing tax imposed for County purposes on Chesapeake and Ohio Railway & Telegraph Co. in Lexington District for year 1895 (signed by A. W. Varner, Commissioner of Revenue), Aug. 31, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing tax imposed for County purposes on Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad in Walkers Creek District for year 1895 (signed by L.L. Watson, Commissioner of Revenue) Sept. 2, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing tax imposed for County purposes on Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad in Natural Bridge District for year 1895 (signed by Charles H. Paxton, Commissioner of Revenue) Sept. 2, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing tax imposed for County purposes on Norfolk and Western Railroad in South River District for year 1895 (signed by Lackey, Commissioner of Revenue) Sept 2, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statement showing tax imposed for County purposes on Norfolk and Western Railroad in Natural Bridge District for year 1895 (signed by Charles H. Paxton, Commissioner of Revenue) Sept 2, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Rockbridge County, VA - School Reports - 1901 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - One document of three pages Annual Report of the Superintendent of Schools for the Year Closing July 31, 1901 [Table N0.3 "Graded Schools" (location, name of principal, post office, whether white or colored, number of grades, number of teachers, whole no. of pupils enrolled, average monthly enrollment, average daily attendance, percent of attendance, no. of months taught, cost of tuition per month per pupil enrolled); Table No. 4 "amount of money available for school purposes during the year;" Table 5 "amount of money paid out during the year + balances on hand and debts due;" Table 11 "private schools in operation during the year." (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Rockbridge County, VA - Commonwealth of Virginia State Personal Property Interrogatories - 1912 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Personal Property Interrogatories re: Mrs. J. M. Black, Chapman S. Irvin, Elijah J. Irvin (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Personal Property Interrogatory re: O. T. Mansfull (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Personal Property Interrogatory re: R. S. Morrison (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Rockbridge County, VA – Share Certificate Rockbridge Alum Springs, Longdale, and Lexington Telephone Company in name of P. M. Engleman (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Share Certificate Rockbridge Alum Springs, Longdale, and Lexington Telephone Company (no apparent date) (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Envelope with typed name of Dr. A. W. Moger / Washington Hall with hand-written note "item enclosed given to me by O.T. Engleman, Jan, 1964" (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Rockbridge County, VA – Misc Records – undated Parchment Muster Rolls and indenture for an 1855 house near Rockbridge County Boat Yard – (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Rockbridge County, VA Misc. (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Staunton Military Enlistment record (likely early Republic period) -- dates appear to be Feb 11 and Feb 18 [17] 99 for Barney Cochran of Armagh, Ireland and Doughty Nicholson of New Jersey (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Undated muster roll of "R.W.Vs." members (Rockbridge Volunteers?) in poor condition (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Indenture for house to be constructed near Rockbridge County Boat Yard by William A. Rapp for Isaac McFaddin and James Kennedy Dec. 21, 1855. House to be completed by Mar 15, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Rockbridge County, VA - Handwritten account of Hunter's Raid from newspaper article that apparently appeared in Lexington Gazette on June 18, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Original handwritten account of Hunter's Raid transcribing newspaper article that apparently appeared in Lexington Gazette on June 18, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Note – "This is a handwritten account of a newspaper article that appeared in the Lexington Gazette on June 18, 1864? [sic]. It is incomplete. McCormick Library Gazette file has only June 1, 1864 issue then skips to July." (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Typewritten transcription of handwritten account of Hunter's Raid from newspaper article that apparently appeared in Lexington Gazette on June 18, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 32)